<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Overview</title>
        <author email="rapruitt(at)users.sourceforge.net">Andy Pruitt</author>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="What Is UpToDater?">
            <p> UpToDater is a database change management tool for agile teams. Database change scripts are
                automatically applied whenever the code associated with the database change is deployed on a server.
	            If you have a large number of database instances, and are deploying new code frequently, UpToDater will
                make your life much more pleasant.</p>
 <p>
                The framework is intended for Java based projects that rely on Ant or Maven.
                The service can run as an application listener or servlet (in a web application), or as an MBean.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="How Does UpToDater Work?">
            <ol>
                <li>Write your database update and migration scripts as pure sql files.</li>
                <li>When you build your application, include the change files with the app. </li>
                <li>When your app is deployed, the UpToDater compares the changes listed in the app with the changes
                that have been previously applied to the database, and runs any changes that have not yet been applied.
                </li>
            </ol>
        </section>
        <section name="Why Should I Use UpToDater?">
            <p>UpToDater allows you to embed database changes in your application deployment bundle (EAR or WAR). UpToDater
            is different from the auto creation facility of your ORM because you specify the exact changes that need to
            occur; nothing occurs behind the scenes or out of your control.  UpToDater also allows you to run data
            migration queries alongside your DDL
            update.  UpToDater means agility for application developers, and peace of mind and control for DBA's. </p>

            <p>With UpToDater, you can always find out what changes have and have not been applied to a database with a
            simple SQL query.</p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>